hi anna
it's so nice to have the opportunity to
have this chat with you and and thank
you so much for making time
um it's been a while hasn't it yeah
how long we've been in touch since 2000
16 16 around there yeah
and the last time i saw you was in
bruges when you came and uh
joined our travels for tomorrow
exploration
thank you so much for that invitation i
love it it was great
so yeah the the the topic of course for
our conversation would be this
exploration that that
is rising all around the world but that
i feel
whether you use the word regenerative or
you didn't use the word regenerative it
doesn't really matter you have been
in this inquiry for um from what my
research
gives me at least 25 years um i mean i
just want to read this one
sentence here what is needed is a small
circle
a small critical mass of um conspirators
both visionaries and practitioners who
are willing
and committed to translate the vision
into practical action
so that all participants in the
community can identify with it
and adopt as appropriate in their
involvement
interests and roles and what is needed
are some courageous leaders standing at
point a of the old tourism curve
with the vision to see how to initiate a
new tourism curve
and in that paper from 1995
um you were speaking to really
both the power of what tourism can do to
connect us
as humanity together and
the deepest functionalities of what
where tourism was heading then
and since then tourism has exploded and
has become such a big
industry that now in in a
pandemic world we're realizing how even
wealthy not not just some beautiful
paradisical island states somewhere in
the global south that
only had tourism as an income but even
really wealthy economies
with big other legs to stand on are
shaken by the fact that their tourism um
industry is is
in danger and i mean i live on the
island of mallorca um
we basically had the economy collapse
here um in the last
two months and the whole of spain
portugal
so many of the southern european nations
have tourism so central
to their economy and and therefore also
to some extent the well-being of a lot
of people
and what's your reading like
i i sense we wanted a sea change
like when we talked in bruges in
september last
year um we were talking about how
tourism can be the motor of the
transformation
towards different type of
re-regionalization and
and and and actually helping local
businesses
thrive in local regenerative economies
thrive
now this this malta seems to have
serious um
problems yeah it's certainly not stuck
it's not starting the way we'd like but
and it's not a motor is it
it's um it's made up of a lot of flawed
living systems called human beings
um yeah i just uh
in conversation with you earlier i just
realized the sort of nature of the
journey in the 1990s
um i was about to leave canada
but in the last few literally the last
year before i
i left i had was able
to spend a lot more time with first
nations people
and i began to get really interested in
uh their world
view um and the whole systems approach
um and that's when i wrote that uh that
paper in 95 and talked about the
medicine wheel
and then and and it's if it's relevant
today it's because
the indigenous people have such a
grounded
holistic view of the world and that's
what we
desperately need at the moment but what
was interesting is i came to europe and
i
i'd also got involved at that time um
with
um technology um i.t
um i it was the birth of the commercial
internet in 1993-94
same year and i did a conference then
with a wonderful man called don tapscott
who's a leader in the i.t movement a
very wise man as it turns out to be
and what that introduced me to for the
next few years which is why in a sense i
pulled back a little bit
on the surface i appeared to pull back
from this
um this line of inquiry because i got
fascinated with the notion that tourism
is a network
it's it's not an industry and the reason
we're in such trouble
is that we're imposing a hierarchical
system of silos and boxes and linear
connections
on what is a living dynamic network and
one of the things
that covert has shown more than anything
else
is just how pervasive that network had
become how
how it had spread almost like a
and a meme or an infection actually
everywhere
it was connected now with everything but
it was still being governed
and structured in people's minds and
operated
as if it were some kind of a vertically
integrated
industry and i think that's one of the
reasons why it collapsed
so quickly if it was a if it was living
according to the natural principles of a
network
a living network
and living according to the and all life
is a network isn't it
if it was really living according to how
that works in nature
it wouldn't have collapsed the way it's
done
it had no resilience it was brittle it's
fragile
and so you have on the one hand a whole
economic sector that has become so
embedded in society
um and yet at the same time it's become
so incredibly fragile
it's an interesting story so the time i
spent in technology
really was helpful it led me into
complexity science and trying to
understand
to be honest with you i found that
almost too much for my brain
um but you don't have to get into the
to the nitty-gritty of all of that to
understand that these principles
these dynamics are what we need to be
consciously applying now
[Music]
what what's your question or have i gone
off on a
um i mean i actually it would be
let's stay there like i i
where do you in in your conversations
with people in the tourism sector
in the last few months um do you sense
that people are actually aware
how fundamental the change is that
has now been triggered um like what i
noticed here on majorca
is that everybody is responding
to the pandemic situation
and trying to come up with um
ways that people can still go to
restaurants or sit at the pool but
maintain social distancing and there's
new protocols being written by the
government that is
that are pages long that now small
tourism businesses that that are
basically
dying and and struggling for to keep the
head above water
are now laden with um
new directives on how if you want to
open you have to do it this way
um and and for me it seems
almost like yesterday i was went finally
we were allowed out here again i went
for a walk and i saw the first couple of
restaurants that
had opened and had we are open come in
and i could see the staff standing there
kind of
twiddling their thumbs and the owner
looking slightly
um shocked and um
and i just really felt for these people
because i feel like this is going to
happen all over mallorca
is there they can open their hotels and
people aren't going to come
no i think well yeah i couldn't agree
with you more i don't
think there's a
there is any real understanding even at
the leadership level in tourism just how
fundamentally
uh uh how deeply affected and how
fundamental this shift is
um it's they keep talking about the
pandemic
and saying it's an unprecedented event
and that is
that's used usually to excuse the fact
that we didn't weren't prepared for it
or we don't know how to handle it
you know it's huge and it's
unprecedented but it
ultimately they're all saying we it will
go away
and in the meantime we're going to use
all of these crazy crazy
measures that undermine the very essence
of
hospitality in the first place i mean
who wants to go out
it means it's a wonderful opportunity
for the whole um
those technocrats that want everything
to be done
by robots to sell their wares
it's proving to be a wonderful
opportunity for for for the it community
that want to invade our privacy and have
us working on apps and
go outside and check your app up so
someone over there that's got covered or
blah blah better run for cover sort of
thing i mean it's all of this stuff is
separating us so it's that separation
model that is
is working um and at the same time with
this focus right now on the pandemic
it's as if climate change has gone away
no one's remembering
the fires in australia last night you
know that was only
six months ago you know so
the notion that we're in that vortex
right now
of a converging of these these
issues whether they're climate change or
biodiversity loss or wealth disparity or
runaway technology they're all still
there and what the pandemic is doing
is revealing our fragility revealing
that a fundamental way of looking at the
world
is not serving us now it did serve us
let's face it
it served us post-war to build the kind
of
lifestyle that many of us have been not
all of us of course
the top 10 or 5 have been enjoying but
unfortunately the decisions are being
made by that top 10
of the global population and we're
living in our own bubble
we're completely unaware of just how
much suffering is going on around the
world
this is this is what happened to me with
this crisis that i had a really
um strong moment of
noticing how deeply touched emotionally
i was by
by the nurses and doctors reporting from
these
the frontline hospitals in italy and
madrid
and and getting really like
deeply over it and then realizing wait a
minute
this has been going on almost through my
entire life in hospitals
all around the global south where people
had to make
these triage decisions of saying there's
too many people starving here
these two won't make it anyway i'm gonna
go to this bed now
and and the horror of that decision
being put in front of any human being
and and
and somehow we've been complicit in in
listening to statistics like that of of
how many hundreds of thousands of people
die of air pollution
millions of people die 42 million people
a year die of
the um effects of urban particle air
pollution
you know that's fascinating we could
wouldn't i agree with you 100
that we think of the people that have
been dying from road accidents exceeds
the number of people that
in the uk i think that die from covet
i'm not sure but i mean there
it's all of a sudden we have just
focused on
on this and done herculean
responses you have to ask why why this
you know is it because it got touched
it got pretty close to the decision
makers i mean even our prime minister
got it
um and i think it shook him up because
he was
prior to getting ill um he was acting
with great sort of
dismissive bravado um because it wasn't
real to him
and i'm even now i'm not sure how how
that how deep
that experience that he had has affected
him
um but yeah it's it's um
i just think in answer to your earlier
question um
i don't think the tourism industry has
has
um woken up to the fact that this is
this is deep change nothing's going to
be the same um
but if we're connected economically is
going to be far far deeper than they are
prepared for i mean my sense is that
there will be
at least 60 percent less tourism
for the next two or three years and
and and what i think most people and
including me can't make a statement
about right now
is that all we've seen at this point is
the effects
to now of the direct impact of the
closures and the virus and
and on the economy um and
what what we're not paying attention to
is
the dominoes that are still falling in
every direction and crisscrossing
causing other dominoes mentioning
complexity theory and
earlier like once you once you have the
training
to think in these systemic networked
ways
and to be able to um
not predicting control but get a sense
of the dynamics of this larger global
system then
we're not paying attention to to um
the warnings that the world health
organization
also ordered i think it was the
agricultural
organization saying that we're running
towards a world where maybe 240 million
people could be starving because of
um not
like the the the locust plagues and um
all the other things that are going on
including
the effects of corbett yeah that's my
point really
um it's the inability to see the in
connections and interdependencies i mean
right now the next thing i would imagine
um is this whole issue around
food security for many places um
you know the whole pacific islands for
example have become so dependent on this
importation of the very food that's
unfortunately killing them
and causing diabetes and and you know
heart disease and so on they've got
about two days of food security
and so we're going to see that
start to happen in our own communities i
think far more
so one thing right now that tourism can
do i think is that it can pivot
it's got to pivot its entire dire uh
focus
um away from the overseas markets and
and focusing on the customer and and
trying it spending millions of dollars
in
bringing people into a place and now
becoming back
part of the community and focusing on
how do we
um make tourism how does how can tourism
contribute
to this community becoming really
healthy
and what we've been suggesting with some
success
and limited success but uh in flanders
for example is
again you were obsessed with growth and
gdp
um but that produced over tourism
because it had to keep growing in order
to make up for the fact that the model
was producing diminishing returns every
year so you had to get bigger and bigger
and bigger
but then of course eventually the
negative impact of that
in terms of the costs of congestion and
resource use and so on
start to bite you in the tail so
yeah yeah so uh model is not working
and now the cobit has shown us okay
we're now going to show you what it's
like
when that comes to you know to stop
um i've got a graph of the drop of
arrivals
the the arrivals pattern into new
zealand for example of people with
non-new zealand passwords
and i suddenly looked at it last night
and it's almost identical to a graph
that was produced
in 1997 of the
collapse of the chord fishery you know
it's that classic
you know exponential upwards but huge
oscillations increasing and then
yeah and we talked about that um but
nobody was listening
now they can see it it's on everybody's
you know
chance so in fact it's back now into
going inward into
land-based um community-based
um resilience building and that's
building community and getting people to
be
thinking as a network but working
contributing to the network not just
extracting from it
that's exactly the shift away from okay
we have a massive problem here but what
is the potential
for what whatever the tourism will turn
into to actually serve um
the communities and the regions where
the tourism is is active in
and and that we started this
conversation
or you you started this conversation a
long time ago but um
last year when when when we met in um
bruges there was a real sense that
more and more people around the world
were having a conversation about
what would a regenerative tourism really
look like how could
tourism industry invest in local food
water energy sovereignty build
resilience infrastructures that on the
one hand would give
the visitors the sense that the money
we're spending is also serving the local
community and more
visitors were starting to demand that
kind of green tourism or
socially engaged tourism and um
uh but
now i i see that for like if i think
about just the majorcan case um
how can i invite the
key players in the large new york and
tourism companies into a conversation
that says
they're going to be a lot less people
coming
they're going to be coming in different
patterns and
the whole offer has to transform like i
i i'm kind of
questioning whether people will
just jump on a plane
to have a little bit of holiday if they
know that the virus is
still out there and they're risking
their family's well-being if if they
just
go on a short trip like the whole kind
of city breaks short
trip break patterns a i think
people won't take the risk e most people
won't have the money because they're
struggling in their own employment
situation or company situation
is like here on mallorca a lot of people
that
had second homes on mallorca um who live
in northern europe and companies in
north northern europe will probably end
up
having to sell their holiday homes in
order to save their companies back home
um and so what's what's your vision in
terms of the
actual pattern change like i i can see
using the infrastructure for
longest day offers where people like for
example retired people
can come for three months but they have
to go through a certain
quarantine phase and then and then
they're
on the island and they can use the
infrastructure um
or educational aspect of working
like engaging with the local community
where it becomes a serving
of the community and the experience in
the community because in in the past
travel was all about seeing with new
eyes
and and learning and people would
ask the question for for most of our
history is it worth me taking the risk
of this journey and and that for a while
wasn't a question that anybody asks
um and it got cheaper and cheaper to fly
and people just did it but i think
that question will be at the center
again and so we need to have offers that
make it worth it
to to travel again
in a different way yeah i agree well i
think
i think the the reality is that the
whether it's six months or two years i
whatever but the the the
international market is going to be um
very slow to pick up um so a destination
now has to say well
how can people travel to us and who will
they be
so get used to the fact that the sheer
volume of numbers isn't going to be
there so you're dealing with a very
different demand
set of demand but really
the best thing that destinations can do
when i say the word destination a
destination is simply a place that
people come to
right it's a way it's it's focusing our
attention on
this place as a recipient or a receiver
of other people
but um so let's maybe not use the word
destination let's use the word community
what does a community need to do right
now
to build back its health and resilience
um and if it focus and the contourism
sector the visitor economy part
can may play a very important role
in that in my opinion but we have to say
how can we as
let's say the island of majorca what are
the various ways that we can try
and keep some of the businesses in the
visitor economy moving uh
with cash flow and starting to explore
healthier ways of being so healthy
reducing their costs growing their own
food reducing their energy requirements
reducing all of those things
becoming more efficient effective as
local producers so really
almost look inward in with the island
who are we how we
as an island going to be able to go
forward
the role of the host economy or which is
another way of describing it
is in fact to start pulling people
together and convening them in
conversations
that's really why i felt tourism had
such a role to play
it is the connector you know it's become
just a transaction
um it's it's in the transactions
business
it's in the numbers business it's all on
spreadsheets but in actual fact the
reality was that it connected
people when we perhaps get this may not
be practical but
in your island but how can we get people
in the
one part of the island coming and
spending time in another part of the
island
and really enjoying their time there
having an exchange of whatever money is
floating around on the island
that keeping is keeping businesses
afloat how can we start to get a
greater integration between the
hotels and the restaurants and the
agricultural business
um how can we you know become much more
self-sufficient how can we address our
food security issues
that's before we even think of just
classic tourism
because if we can build a degree of
resilience
and if we can show as a as a place
and that we care about this place and
we're doing everything we can
to bring it back to health we will be in
a
very good position to attract the kind
of visitor
that is looking for that i mean i was
very surprised i'm going to read you a
quote
um it was in the in a magazine in
business magazine
in new zealand it was from the head of
the new zealand
trade and export council and he was
saying that um
about you know they've got a halo effect
from from the reputation for having
a pandemic but he's saying the
um the food and beverage opportunity is
at the sharp end of that
the world is hunting for health hunting
for countries that
care for their people and care for their
environment
so if if a base is going to come out of
this it has to start
caring for example there are
we've got a major problem of uh the
covet
attacking people in in homes care homes
right because we've parked our elderly
in places where they but they actually
are now incredibly vulnerable
you know we put them all together in a
in a hermetically sealed box and then
once that environ that
virus gets in why aren't we finding ways
of getting
people in that community the elderly
community
more engaged outdoors being able to
participate not just parking them
how could we find different ways of
utilizing that that knowledge base that
that talent base that wisdom base that's
just one silly idea
another is that you know and again it
was a wonderful example in flanders
they have an incredibly strong social
tourism
[Music]
community they have a network of 2000
players that's
entrepreneurs that's people in the care
business
uh in every kind of um help
you know social uh endeavor and the
municipalities that deliver social
services and they've created a network
of 2000 players such that
if somebody has seen or identifies
themselves as desperately needing a
break they've been a carer for
a sick person in their family and
haven't had a break for weeks
or if they're financially challenged or
if they have a disability
have a network whereby they can be a
holiday can be tailor-made for them
now what that's doing for the commercial
sector is they have a lot of spare
capacity in this seasonal business
so they're often able to offer a holiday
to someone at a very very
very low price but it keeps the it keeps
the lights on it keeps the business
going
but it was to me that was saying you
know we are not just here to attract the
wealthy that it can afford to flip on a
plane
we're here to be part of the network
part of what is makes our society worth
having
am i making any sense my examples aren't
as good as they could be
it's all wonderful tell me a little bit
more about the um
like i i saw to some extent i saw the
first
crescendo of the travel to tomorrow
program that you
helped curate um but it's been a two
year journey
up to that wonderful summit in that
church in bruges where
michelle holliday and and rob hopkins
and andrew sims
um were among the speakers and
and me which i thought it was wonderful
that you brought
four people who aren't in their primary
kind of activity space daily focused on
tourism
to address how many were we two hundred
and some
um tourism hundreds of people there yeah
and yeah but i would love you to tell
the story of that whole like
how did you engage with flanders and how
do you see
what what did the program change so far
and how has it changed now that that
um the pandemic um has happened
well i i can certainly go into a bit of
the history um
uh yeah i was uh it was back in 2016
which was when the whole overtourism
issue
erupted really um there there was
resident backlash in barcelona and riots
and it's the word overtourism was coined
or brought before by
by um a prominent travel
industry business magazine and
all of a sudden it appeared like over
tourism was erupting
almost as a plague in different parts of
the world because
the pressure points were where you just
had too many people
coming in at the time so venice was
another example
and flonders is right next to the
netherlands
and um amsterdam as well amsterdam is
also suffering from the success
of its own promotion um and
the ceo of flanders was saying we have
to avoid this
which was smart and he was also smart by
asking good questions he said what kind
of tourism do we want how do we balance
um our desire to maintain our culture
and share it with others but not be
overrun
um and not lose in a sense not so much
control but
what may be control of what we have to
offer so he just he brought me in to
start
um you know to my brief was to be
provocative and i suppose most of my
work really in the last few years has
been bringing
some of these fresh ideas about um
deep power and shifting deep deep
cultural shifting that the work you do
obviously
daniel so well trying to bring that to
an industry is that it's completely
um unaware of this kind of thinking
and bring down the fact that you know
living in this
vortex of of uncertainty and complexity
that would require us to deal very
differently than we've done
in the past so that led to a number of
us
sessions one of the again that flanders
is extremely good at
is that and they have the wealth that
they have a
large community of people responsible
for for tourism development
at the community level but they were
able to bring both private sector and
the public sector together
for a series of meetings around the
country and
gradually over a period of time we were
able to introduce the fact that
you know growth in itself of numbers
was not really benefiting the country if
the costs were not identified
or mitigated in other words you could
have a situation
where you had a lot more people
producing a lot less benefit or even
negative benefit
if you didn't take those into account
and that really perhaps a more
systems approach a living systems
approach would say
how can these communities start to
flourish and
thrive across a number of dimensions
and this is not new i mean we're looking
at
countries of which new zealand is one
many
are now not many but a number are saying
what are we here for is it just to
produce more gdp
which is no measure of well-being or are
we here to produce
greater well-being so um it was in that
sort of context that i was
able to start to talk about tourism as a
living system
as a network and that a successful
network
human living system would be like an
ecosystem it would have to flourish
across multiple dimensions and that
caught on
so we started group experimenting taking
small
small regions but this whole notion of
trouble to tomorrow was again something
the market has created which i thought
was really good
and it became a focal point for thinking
about doing things differently
the other thing that florentis is really
good at is this notion of collecting
stories and telling stories of
individuals
making their contribution so what that
does
is again it mirrors back to people this
is not
some theoretical idea it's happening in
our own community now
and the question becomes how do we
nurture that how do we nourish it
and so that that then results in this
other positive feedback loop because
people say i can get involved in that
nurturing process
so that was the history there um now
because of various contractual reasons i
think basically i i've
i've i've had to step back i mean i i
there are only so much like
i can do but there now are um
if you like a group of enthusiastic
change agents
embedded in the community
and linkages are being made now which i
find exciting with
um with other sectors of the economy so
it's a question of watch this space
because to me
the irony is it's a bit like how how
does uh
how does a virus um infect us
um what we're looking at is taking the
meme
of a flourishing regenerative type of
tourism that
that nurtures development and growth
we're trying to
ins and put that meme into the community
and have it spread that notion is
actually one that
um interesting the quote you gave
earlier with
of the new zealand um tourism official
um because i
i have experienced that
even before i started working with the
term regenerative
i um highlighted always that really the
measure of um
wise decision-making is the emergence of
health and wholeness and
and well-being across the system at
different scales and even wrote a phd on
design for human and planetary health
what i've noticed is
that people through this obviously
through this covert
19 situation the word health has hit
home
to people in a whole new way and the
link between ecosystems and planetary
health
and human health and population health
is now not something that a few
academics and a few
futurists um talk about or that
planetary health alliance talks about
but but everybody is starting to to get
that and
um i think it is
at the center and in your 1995 paper
that i
quoted from earlier you said that
tourism is a healing profession and the
way that you speak of it
that network of living networks
i can i can see that that's
that's really the essence of when we're
exploring regenerative tourism how how
do we
create a tourism that is for itself
but is also part of a larger whole
gives back more than it takes because
that is actually the
if increasingly the essence
of being regenerative is to
dance between that polarity
of in for oneself and being part of a
larger hole in service to life
that's how you reconcile and and
more question because you've worked in
mexico and and in new zealand also on
similar projects or with with similar
people trying to
explore this and i just would love you
to give a little bit of a flair from
your experience all over the world
in in the tourism industry of how you
see this conversation
popping up in different places like my
sense is that the regenerative
tourism conversation is is almost more
advanced than latin america than it
has been in europe what's what's your
sense
well certainly um i think the
the regenerative conversation is is more
advanced there it's
the term has been used there much
earlier than here
um but i i i was thinking while you're
asking me this
the work i did in with flanders and and
it wasn't just me there were a lot of
other people that
were already setting the stage the folks
in social tourism the folks and
they were doing this huge storytelling
exercise which was so
helpful it was no it was it was
softening the soil
if you like um but all that work that we
took place between 2017
and 19 was done without really using the
word regeneration at all
and in fact i think in my own work i
feel
um by by putting too much focus on
regenerative to it's a mouthful
anyway it's hard to explain
um from from cold but when we talk about
building creating um a place that cares
which is what this this uh ceo this
trade
export council was saying i think that
that resonates or links really well with
this interest now
in in health and well-being if you can
demonstrate
as a place that you care about your
place you care about the people
you care about the rest of life in that
place so you don't have dirty waterways
you aren't
um open pit mining you know and
and putting people in danger you you are
trying to create an economy
that is healthy that you are caring
about each other
that is when um and and tourism as you
as you
as i really identified um is fascinating
to me because
the word um hospitality is the same
route as
hospice and hospital it's about caring
it's about holding it's about making
people whole
so we're in that business anyway so
you know i know i'm rambling a bit but i
think it's it's
it's it's this focus away from selling
something to someone else
outside and now coming back and making
this place
a healthy whole caring place that will
attract
this is the difference it will naturally
people who are seeking those values
you know so it's standing head and
shoulders i say look at look at
the flowers you know they don't have
marketing plans and marketing
expenditure they just
each flower is doing its flower thing
it's being who it is and it's attracting
a certain kind of bee it doesn't affect
all of them
so can't we take that analogy in tourism
well it reminds me of one of my
most important mentors brian goodwin um
he said to me once daniel it's much more
important to be the center of attraction
rather than the center of attention
yes that's beautiful i'll remember that
one that is the point
we we we know that people gravitate
to people who are full of vitality and
energy and enthusiasm
provided that they also are full of
empathy
and caring you know you can have
vitality and enthusiasm and be a
narcissistic bastard
and no one really wants to hang around
you very much
you might get a lot of attention but
you're not going to attract people into
your community
around you um and this is the same in
tourism
constantly are saying how can we be the
best
i said you know just be yourself nobody
else can be
you this for me this is like as you were
speaking as
as reminded of my
my highest hope like if if the five
big players in tourism here on on the
island that i live on and i keep coming
back to mallorca because i just happened
to
choose to live on an island that is so
dependent on tourism and
and almost responsible for the kind of
tourism that we now see in the world
like
the the people that are still alive
today they're still the patriarchs of
these
large tourism empires were the ones that
that developed the kind of um
holiday village all-inclusive tourism
that has spread all over the world and
they've started here with a few
hotels because of the beauty of this
island and now they have empires of
400 500 hotels all around the world and
um what i feel at this
unique point where governments will have
to take
money into their hands that previously
they would never have
been willing to just unleash for a
transformative process because it would
have endangered the economy
now that we've endangered the economy
already and
when we're in kind of
a different mode um similarly
in spain there was always there's always
the saying panpara
amber para like the big tourism players
were saying
the money is still coming in what are
you talking to me about
like i'm doing something right here um
i'm i'm getting wealthier
so who are you you little consultant
talking to me that i have to do
something else
um yeah you can make a lot of money out
of slavery too
but but if every well just
that's a close to the born comment about
tourism and and how some of them are
optimizing their gains from it but the
um the sense that i what the division
and i would have
for mallorca is a local
friend of mine and and very respected um
kind of practice and thought leader here
on the island who does a lot
like i call him the leonardo da vinci of
majorca because he's
a stonemason and
everything like builds archery and he
he's
uh launched a project which is called
balearesvert
um with the idea of planting a million
um trees in fruit forests all over the
island
not one big food forest but wherever
somebody's got a piece of land that they
are willing to donate into this process
getting people in
and increasing the amount of forest
cover on the island but bioproductive
food productive
forest cover that we can use to start a
biomaterials economy on the island that
is circular that we can
increase food sovereignty with that we
can
heal the hydrological cycle bring back
the rain hold the rain in the ground
all those things that it would do if we
planted a million trees and
built the soil to nurture them and
retain the water to feed them
and for me a really bold leadership
vision right now
on this island would be to say okay
here's the industry tourism
yeah all these provider industries 45
of this island's economy is tourism 80
percent
if you include the providers it's 80 of
the islands economy
we can either live off government
handouts
just about twiddling their funds
watching telethinko until
the planes start arriving again or we
can say the next two years
we're just going to have we will only
allow
40 of the tourism that we had before
even if they wanted to come
maybe less and we will pay people
to help get this island shipshape again
to heal this island
to make this the most attractive
destination in the future
since we've got two or three years until
this
multiple waves of this virus will get to
a point where the virus gets
less virulent and and the situation
will maybe adjust itself nobody knows
let's use it
and do exactly that heal the island
build the local resilience build food
sovereignty energy
sovereignty water sovereignty rebuild
the soils
and put in the infrastructure that we
use waste water to irrigate dry lands
and um we we could do it
uh but it but it and and i i feel like
while for most tourism players this kind
of conversation
feels like it's a diversion from core
business
and that's not what we do ultimately
they rely on the beauty health and
resilience of
the destinations in which well that's
what
yeah you're saying with a lot more
illustrative
um examples with what i'm basically
saying as well
i think the challenge in majorca is that
the um
[Music]
that probably um
the tourism industry's wealth has been
quite concentrated in the hands of a few
big
players but the reality is throughout
europe
is that generally speaking 95 to 98
of the participants the suppliers in
tourism are small medium-sized
enterprises
so it's at the community level i think
um and i don't you know
i don't know the island well but but
it's really
getting this idea of this vision now
amongst the young people of majorca that
you know also sitting idly and wondering
what's going to happen to them
um i think you know to sort of infect
them with
this vision that we don't want 20 years
from now to be in a similar situation
the second pro the second message of
course is that
we may get on top of the pandemic but
it's all these other factors are not
going away i mean the next thing
you know could be drought we could go
through a period of drought we could
you know the the um uh yeah it's just
that
the economy is again another big issue
you're still
dependent with your tourism economy on
people having enough disposable income
in your uh origin source markets to be
able to come to new york
and that may not be the case either
exactly so um
right now i'm saying to people if you've
got a bit of land start learning how to
grow on it
you might be very grateful a few years
from now but the tourism industry if
they can start to realize the connection
between as you say
uh shade food water
um going back to hosting if you like
maybe the tourism industry starts to
host
parties of people who've come together
for the purpose of
growing things um you know what i'm
saying go back to that idea as we're the
we're the hub in the community we pull
people together where ideas like this
can
can circulate and and ferment and
percolate
in this this vision of could the tourism
industry in this
like if they if they just accept that
the crisis like this
if they start thinking in terms of two
or three years response rather than this
immediate response because what's
happening with the immediate response is
that the regulations the government is
writing
around how you can reopen your hotel is
making it impossible to be a
responsible hotel anymore because
basically it's all about
one way like how often do you have to
change it
we have to change this plastic apron and
these plastic gloves and this
the amount of product that is is
where we're just having the conversation
about deplastifying the tourism industry
and they were doing a good job here on
majorca when a lot of the
the chains of really kind of taking that
serious in the last year and and now all
the new regulations
it's all out of the window everything is
very high
um you only use once disposable
security equipment that supposedly keeps
people from
from being that's exactly the the
response you would expect from this
entire
mechanical materialistic world view it's
that we can manage it and control it
and you end up just if it wasn't dead
before you've destroyed it
i mean the whole reason to come to an
island like new yorker is to sit in an
open-air cafe and watch people
you know conversing and and music and
dancing and touching each other and all
the rest of it
all the stuff that we you know reserve
northerners in europe want to
experience right so um no i think it's
crazy
if i were an island i'd say the most
important thing and that's why i think
new zealand
is an island country but you're an
island within spain
is to say how do we make our island how
do we build its immune system
so that this becomes a really healthy
place where
pandemics like this cannot you know
spread how do we put in place
if you're going to have any
interventions it's more about how do you
protect the island
from infection from outside but the best
way of resisting disease is to build an
immunity system
so that you know there's a whole idea of
putting people to stay inside for months
on end
and completely you know not have
sunlight not have fresh air and all of
the rest of it
is also bizarre because you're you're
draining their
immunity system that's why i was talking
about the care home situation
so if we can go back to this idea of how
do we build a healthy community a
flourishing community in our own right
and then have the opportunity of
extending the invitation
because we really know who we are and
what we stand for and we know the kind
of people that are going to want to
are attracted to us we then just simply
invite we don't have to pummel them to
death with
with endless advertising and promotional
things
we just say this is who we are what
we're doing people will want to come
to see it to experience it
i think it's it's better than the ones
we've got at the moment
i i was working on
a pathway to engage tourism in this
vision of bringing
common land foundation and and the
ecosystems restoration camp foundation
um in
in like basically almost weaving that
with this impulse of the
baleau's web proposal and say okay we we
could actually
create a 20-year strategy
of making this land more productive
of increasing the forest increasing our
capacity to store water and
of building an entirely
combustion engine free um transport
system that
is available to people who need to move
and isn't based on private
vehicles but on it allows people to move
around the island
on renewably like powered by renewable
energy all of that
could as you as you hinted at that could
be part of the new offer
but that is the new offer that's the
what that guy was saying about the world
is hunting for health and hunting for
countries that care for their people and
their environment
i believe that's the market of the
future if you talk about the quality
market
you know everyone's saying volume to
equality and blah blah blah and that's
not just about getting rich people
spending a pilot you know
coming into a five-star resort it's
about people who want
the the are looking for they're looking
to be made
they're looking for health they're
looking for for an experience in
a safe healthy environment we know that
the natural world is healing
we know that the demand for nature is
going up like crazy
so why not just focus on being the
primary example of that in the
mediterranean
turning the clock almost back in terms
of the biological
health you know when those places were
full of orange groves and
and then they became covered by by
concrete
but the nightmare like new yorkers in a
perfect place to do this
in spain the day that i
came back i had to shortcut a visit to
portugal
um because of the the
beginning of lockdowns everywhere and so
on and i arrived the day that the
um national state of halan was declared
here on majorca
and um asked the taxi driver and he said
oh they're going to close the airport
tonight and so on and i said to the
taxi driver um
and majorca used to be the island of
calm
yeah yeah boy did i
why was i right it was so incredibly
quiet here on the island
i live near the airport the airplanes
are not flying and
um and so many major cans
their soul was hungry
to return the island of calm
they don't know how they're going to
feed their families so we need to we
need to
somehow do the classic regenerative
thing of how do we
get out of this polarity and see the
potential
of um actually making la
isla de la calma if you could
if you could pass away because you need
someone with some resources but if you
could
persuade one or two of the
the older families in in mallorca that
have benefited from this phenomenal
growth over the last 20 years
and built international empires if you
can persuade them to make this their
legacy piece
is to bring back the calm and the
you know the health of this island as
there
and get them and then the next thing is
is to really
fill what i consider to be a growing
vacuum
and vacuums can be useful uh there's a
that is another word for the hunger that
is existing how can we get out of this
predicament
we don't go want to go back to the noise
but we don't know how
so okay um i don't have a checklist of
answers exactly how
and now that you if we both did we'd be
quite wealthy
but you know where is the intelligence
for that it's in the community
so maybe you you can get someone to
support the id
get the vision but then support a whole
series of
once you are out of the lockdown phase
where you can't meet
you know because that has that will
happen
i don't know what the infection rate is
on new york are acceptable
when you've got to that point then you
can have
small gatherings how can we start to
seed
a whole pile of conversations in
different parts of the island
and also have them linked digitally as
well
where they celebrate what is great about
our community what do we love about here
what are the produce that we we think we
do best and
blah blah blah you know but turn it
around something tangible not just ideas
not not
concepts but get people talking and
caring again
and out of that i think that makes
since we need to increase our food
security rapidly
and to prepare for what's coming and
it's it's a
clear maybe use food and the hospitality
making
people make it possible to meet and
convene
but the focus is on on food and health
and the work that you've because you
work you got caught in new zealand with
all this
and and you were working with people in
the bay of plenty on on a
um project helping them
rethink their well yeah i mean they
what well the bear plenty basically um
is one of the
one of 30 regions in new zealand
and they had re-completely revamped
their whole strategy and one of the
things that was really great about it
was
the amount of community engagement
i mean they didn't just come up with a
strategy which often these
dmos do they went out and found out
what um what the community cared about
what they wanted what they didn't want
to see
because it wasn't one of the hot spots
in new zealand it's it's a beautiful
part of the
of the country so they did a lot of that
so there was that sense of engagement
there they also did some work on what
they call their dna
so what is it that is unique about us
and how can we express that um and they
brought
the importance of the resident
population really
caring or loving their own destination
so bringing that those emotions of
affection and pride and so on
um so they began to weave in some if you
like
regenerative concepts of bring putting
more back in than
than taking out so um they were about to
launch this strategy
we had at the very time that this whole
pandemic thing
was breaking and so we had some good
sessions
and and i was fortunate enough to be
uh to one of the sessions where i um you
remember that beautiful poem that came
out of
you know the what is the voice of govid
um it's asking us to stop
and reflect it's a beautiful poem i'm
sure you're familiar with it's
italian i think it was a sculptor it was
called
and i was able to read a bit of that
poem and what i what
really um impressed me was was the
resonance
at a human level it moved people they
realized that this
message was what they wanted to hear at
the same time their businesses were
going
you know were tanking so um
the challenge i think right now is that
um
you've got you know this this this
emotional
almost spiritual desire to to build
something new
but you've got the reality of paying
your bills
and you've got the reality of the
organizational structure
of what the budget is going to be and
who's going to do what and all the rest
of it
so where we're at with that is that
michelle holliday and i
felt that you know we couldn't bring
people together in groups because of the
lockdown that we would try and
develop an online program that people
could start to get involved in
um over the winter months and
just get some of these ideas that we're
talking about now
discussed in their communities but have
some access to information and ideas
so that the the recovery could gradually
move in that regenerative
direction but that would be specifically
for communities in
the bay of plenty area well you know
it's we've just
where we're at at the moment is trying
to um interest the
30 regional tourism organizations
in uh subscribing to an online course
that could then be made available to all
of the businesses in their area
in other words instead of us trying to
sell online course to individual
businesses we would
sell it to the to the region and then
they could just make it available
and this was before their lockdown is is
being lifted
um they've done an exceptional job in
new zealand of
taming the virus as it were so they're
actually going back to allowing
small group meetings of 100 people but
the idea was to find a mechanism
of seeding i think that's the best way
of putting it
some of these regenerative concepts
amongst the tourism community and
getting conversations going
um while you were down there did you
connect because
there's a huge amount of amazing
regenerative practitioners particularly
in the auckland bay area and what's
so powerful is that more than half of
them
um of maori or
origin and have realized how
to some extent what all this
regenerative development and
regenerative design and regenerative
practice conversation is
trying to do is to come back to a wisdom
that they've been holding
for centuries which brings us back to
the beginning of your story of
your time in canada where you learn so
much from well
the maori i mean i've i have been to i
went out to new zealand to do a phd in
and that's when i realized that i wasn't
suited for academia
um i found it too too confining um
but that's when i was first exposed to
the maori uh community and then i spent
a lot of time in the south pacific
it's a polynesian uh culture
um but yes um this is the beautiful
thing about new zealand
is that it has this wealth
of wisdom right in its midst
and what i'm saying is this program that
we're developing
um i'm trying to reach out to the maori
community who've been very supportive of
me
personally in my presentations and so on
and said
we we have to do this together this has
to be
um has to weave in through it throughout
it
the the maori wisdom because you have
that that resource
i made some contact with sir um caroline
um davidson who's in with cabal
and the regenerative practitioners um
at the moment and there's also i made
contact with um
hugh jelly who's leading the whole
regenerative agriculture movement
in in new zealand and i'm trying to you
know again
we need to bring bring all this together
so you know it's it's tentative it's
difficult
uh i was in uh i was in like lockdown
isolation for
for the time i was there with very poor
internet so
there were limits to what we could do um
but we started something and um
yeah we'll see how it goes we'll keep
working on it
one more question so we don't make this
recording to too long
yeah i'm sorry anybody who's still
listening to it is already
very committed because we make like
we've rambled a bit too
but we had a conversation this is what
people think
the um you mentioned just before we
started to record you mentioned
um that you're part of this group that
is more of an academic group
that was looking into tourism and
climate change
and a couple of times skirted on this
that of course
on the one hand there is a role for
tourism there is a
importance and like so many people's
wealth
like families livelihood depend on
tourism
on the other hand it was part of driving
climate change in a in
in a dangerous way and so um
[Music]
you mentioned that you put some ideas
towards this group of academics
and were somewhat surprised to actually
see them land
like what what what is your take on how
tourism as as a as a global
network needs to respond
to what is the much bigger
danger on the horizon of cataclysmic
climate change
and and how to reinvent itself to not be
be complicit in driving it but actually
being
active an active agent in avoiding
runaway climate change
well i mean tourism is a very large
industry with hundreds of thousands of
people involved in
and there are a lot of people uh
individuals um particularly and some
institutions that
have been very concerned about its
contribution to
carbon emissions um the aviation
um portion of that is of main concern
so um i would hate for there to be any
implication that there isn't an awful
lot of
really good thinking and work going on
on that
um but then kovit came along and now
everyone's focused on recovery from
covet and
climate change has sort of proceeded in
the background what i think we have to
do is bring back that climate change
issue
and show that this the the the way of
approaching
dealing with climate change is the same
as the way of
avoiding a pandemic it's all intel into
relink it's a system
and just the very idea that we created
the covet pandemic it didn't appear
out of the blue it wasn't sent by the
gods to punish us
we created the conditions that enabled
those viruses to mutate
and until we take responsibility for
that and why did we do that because
we're
a con society that's consuming way
beyond
the earth's capacity to to uh to keep up
with us
and we're destroying uh forests etc etc
so it's a constantly a talk of
of of showing the interdependence the
interconnection and breaking down these
silos of thinking that exist in our
heads
and has certainly exist in our
institutions that's the first task
um and i think kovid's done an awful lot
to help us in that regard
whether you know so is that an answer to
your question because i
tend to think and forget me
it is a bit of a paradox this whole the
how important it is to stay able to
travel and build
global solidarity and connections and
maintain that network of
that ultimately is part of connecting us
into one human family on one
planet that we deeply depend upon and at
the same time
um finding the right
measure again of when to travel how long
to travel how often to travel
i think we we've kind of gone
for a decade or two we were just beyond
proportions
of these these um fast turnover
trips um there were two you know there's
two kinds of travel that really
in my opinion were doing the harm and
one it was the cheap travel where no one
in that
value chain was paying the true price of
it
the consumer wasn't because it was being
offered you know the 25
uh pound flights from london to nice for
example for a you know
for a party this weekend that that has
to stop
and it will stop because as cheap travel
is not
you can expect that as we come out of
this
um come out of this and plane start
flying it will be a lot more expensive
so that impulse just go because it's
cheap won't be there
which is important the other
contribution to the problem
was that something like uh 75
of the emissions were contributed by
15 of the flyers
or even less than that i'm not good at
numbers
but that proportion and that was because
there were certain people in the
population would again
they weren't necessarily trivial trips
they think they were important trips
they were going to see the banker they
were going to have meetings
this constant business related flying
and so on or it could be
you know someone in ghana who's really
wealthy and just pops back at the
weekend to see
their kids in the private school they're
in right so there was an awful lot of
what i call elitist excessive travel
that was contributing to the emissions
if you take that out and you look at
what we're left with in the next two
years we could have it's not the end of
international travel or flights
you know we are global we are now a
planet we are now connected
i think it will will start to regulate
itself but the most important thing
is that we develop really
um uh attractive and
meaningful opportunities for travel um
within our own within our own spaces
so that that need to jump on a plane
um is not as as great as it was but that
need was really a manufactured one in
the sense that we could do it
but i think most people who were doing
those kind of trips came back more
exhausted than they were
i mean what you just spoke to is so
typically
actually myokin and character um when
when
when you like i've lived here now for
ten years and quite often when you when
you say to people i'm going to
california and people would say um why
do you
want to go to california go to
philanthropy looks the same
then you say i'm going to galicia well
go to uk looks the same so because the
island is so diverse
in a very on a very small island and it
is actually true that you could
that's why so much of the audio visual
industry likes using this
as a place to shoot films because you
actually have such a diversity of
landscapes so
in many ways they somehow it's in the
myokine soul
to to say we live in the best place we
don't need to travel anywhere
but if that attitude exists then use
that to harness this
re revitalization of the place so people
from one end of the island are
encouraged
to go and visit people at the other end
of the island and exchange ideas and so
on
but um yeah i would say that's the
strength you have if they're
you know sufficiently aware that they
have uh the world in microcosms on the
island
well thank you so much for this
conversation we could go on but
um this has been really rich and i
yeah as soon as this is lift up
i would love to come and explore with
you um it sounds
because i really have i do believe in
our islands we
are great places to work with i was in
the azores and they've doing some very
interesting things there and i've got an
interest in the pacific
and they're incredibly vulnerable um and
i think
you know what we could do it's important
that we try and support them
because we've we've basically extracted
so much wealth and pleasure out of those
places
with putting very little back in no i
mean that's that's i moved to mallorca
because majorca is
the right size for being an example of
regional regeneration so it's it's a
regional case study and i think islands
because they come in different shapes
and sizes um
their wonderful uh
field study opportunity to for for
regional transformation and in this
healing of the landscape and healing of
the relationship between people and
landscape
um that we actually need to do
everywhere around the world but it's
it's a little bit easier to do
well it's difficult in one way but it's
also easier and another
to do it on islands because they're well
defined
and um and i think that
unleashing like if if we find examples
of how
regional tourism players on 10 15
islands around the world became
active catalysts of that turnaround
to help be healers of their islands
and reinvent themselves that
lesson will then also go on to the
mainland that would be a really
catalytic example and again it would
those destinations who lead
with that kind of vision will be um
remembered in the future and will will
be centers of um
attraction right now i agree and i think
because you can get a lot more
um you're going to get results faster on
an island
um because they're onto all of the
distractions of having these flows from
outside
you can focus more so yes i agree let's
do that let's let's
find examples and share them yeah i
would love to work with it with you
on one of them but you'd have to come to
majorca
now you stay there and look after that
beautiful daughter of yours and your
beautiful wife and uh and
and majorca we need you there okay thank
you so much
[Music]